Guide to the Britton Collection of Early Texas and U.S. Civil War documents, 1597-1903 MS 009
Woodson Research Center, Rice University, Houston, Texas
Britton Collection of Early Texas and U.S. Civil War documents
1597-1903
Woodson Research Center, Rice University, Houston, Texas https://library.rice.edu/woodson
Britton, Mr. & Mrs. James Lanier
MS 009
3 Linear Feet (2 boxes)
Legal documents and correspondence related to the Jose de Escandon expedition of the Gulf Coast (1765-1766) and the establishment of missions in the Seno Mexicano, and U.S. Civil War and Reconstruction documents, as well as other documents related to Texas and American history.
Scope and Contents
Legal documents and correspondence related to the Jose de Escandon expedition of the Gulf Coast (1765-1766) and the establishment of missions in the Seno Mexicano, and U.S. Civil War and Reconstruction documents, as well as other documents related to Texas and American history.
Access Restriction
This material is open for research.
Conditions Governing Access
Box 1 stored off-site at the Library Service Center. Please request this material via woodson@rice.edu or call 713-348-2586.
Box 2 stored onsite in the vault.
Acquisition Information
Gifts of Mr. and Mrs. James Lanier Britton, 1971.
Index Terms
Subjects
War; Frontier life
Document Types
legal documents; letters (correspondence)
Places
Texas; United States
Subjects (Persons)
de Alvarez, Ellicendo; Britton, Mr. & Mrs. James Lanier
- Series I: Documents, 1597-1800, 3988
  - Ellicendo de Alvarez documents, 1597, 3991 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Papers relating to Escandon expedition and establishment of Missions in the Seno Mexicano, mid-18th century, 3990 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - American Declaration of Independence collection, n.d.-1800, bulk: 1755-1800, 3989 (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Series II: Documents, 1861-1903, 3973
  - Treasurer's warrant as pay for Texas Rangers signed by Gov. Sam Houston, Jan. 11, 1861, 3987 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Abraham Lincoln broadside: original Emancipation Proclamation as issued in General Orders #1, Jan. 2, 1863, 3986 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Broadside signed by J.Y. Dashiell re: Gov. Lubbock's order transferring state troops to the Confederacy, Aug. 5, 1863, 3985 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Receipt for 1200 pounds fodder bought from Robert Brantley, signed by N.A. Burge, Nov. 12, 1863, 3984 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Certificate of Deposit for $1500 to be invested… signed by James Sorley, April 13, 1864, 3983 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Emergency Confederate warrant for removal of safe containing archives, Oct. 6, 1864, 3982 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Exchange certificate for $4000 converting old issue to new issue, Dec. 8, 1864, 3981 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Amnesty oath of T.F. Hollis, July 21, 1865, 3980 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Broadside directing confiscation of Texas archives, July 22, 1865, 3979 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Five John Steele letters, Jan.-May 1866, 3978 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Jefferson Davis clothing order, May 1, 1866, 3977 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Reconstruction appointment of Samuel Harper, July 11, 1872, 3976 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Proxy: N.Y. & Texas Land Co.-Wm. M. Rice, Sept.25, 1900, 3975 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Albert T. Patrick to Gen. H.B. Stoddard, Aug. 26, 1903, 3974 (Box 1, Folder 17)
- Series III: Imprints, 1793-1963, 3966
  - House of Representatives imprints, 1860-61, 1864-65, 1867-68, 1872, 3972 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Senate imprints, 1862, 1864, 1866, 3971 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Misc. imprints, 3970 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Presidents collection imprints, 1793, 1799, 1802, 1820, 1832, 1836, 1839, 1841, 1842, 1843, 3969 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Presidents collection imprints, 1845, 1850, 1852, 1854, 1860, 1861, 1868, 1871, 1878, 3968 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Presidents collection imprints, 1881, 1885, 1890, 1898, 1908, 1912, 1918, 1921, 1931, 1941, 1945, 1958, 1963, 3967 (Box 1, Folder 23)
- Series IV: Oversize materials
  - Hand-drawn chart (Box 2)